<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>5k on LIMINAL RUNNER</title><link>https://LiminalRunner.com/categories/5k/</link><description>Recent content in 5k on LIMINAL RUNNER</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 23:46:24 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://LiminalRunner.com/categories/5k/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>5k Plan: (Final) Week 8</title><link>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week8/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 23:46:24 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week8/</guid><description>&lt;p>Weekly Update #4&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This was the last week of the 8 week 5k Plan I have been following. The good news, I got my 5k paced run done. The bad news, I am sick/hurt at the moment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, here is the weekly overview:
&lt;img src="https://LiminalRunner.com/img/weekly/garmin2020-w27.jpg" alt="weekly_stats_2020_week27">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Monday was a tempo run, going through multiple paces, nothing new but good fun.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did my &amp;ldquo;timed&amp;rdquo; 5k run on Thursday because I was not sure if I could get a run in on Friday or Saturday.&lt;br>
The &lt;a href="https://www.nike.com/pdf/Nike-Run-Club-5K-Training-Plan-Audio-Guided-Runs.pdf">Nike Run Club 5k Training plan&lt;/a> gives a whole table of paces for people in different states of fitness/ability. Because it has been a while since I ran i started this plan on the slowest level of their pace table.
That translates to&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th style="text-align:center">1k pace&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:center">5k pace&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:center">10k pace&lt;/th>
&lt;th style="text-align:center">recovery pace&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:center">7:30&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:center">7:55&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:center">8:10&lt;/td>
&lt;td style="text-align:center">9:00&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>This would translate to a 12:00 mile pace, you can do the rest of the math yourselves. :)&lt;br>
Following this pace, this would set me up with a 39:30 5k time. I am aware that this is super slow. But I am just competing against myself and not against others. For me this is about finishing it and having fun doing it. Getting faster is something that will come with time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For the run itself I did about an 800m warmup followed by a few minutes of dynamic stretches. In the last weeks I always felt sluggish on my long runs without having a proper warmup because i thought that at an easy recovery speed I don&amp;rsquo;t need one (the training plan also didn&amp;rsquo;t mention one, but does in interval/tempo/fartlek/hill workouts). With this warmup I was ready to go, no sluggish feeling!&lt;br>
Just for the hell of it I did it without looking at my watch to get a gps pace estimate.&lt;br>
Keep in mind the table above with the paces I was going for, here are the &amp;ldquo;personal records&amp;rdquo; I set this run:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://LiminalRunner.com/img/weekly/garmin2020-w27pr.jpg" alt="weekly_stats_2020_week27pr">&lt;br>
The first km was the 6:37min/km time, up till the 3k mark, i continued running below 7:00 min/km. Around the 3k mark I had to slow down to a slow jog for a around 20 seconds to get my breathing under control. I finished running an 7:10 min/km average for the whole distance, which means I was 4min faster than the pace I was aiming for. On one side, I now know that I can run a 5k faster than the target pace I set for myself which sounds good, on the other side, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t pace myself at all. As I said, after 3k my breathing was all over the place. This is something I am not happy about. I guess if i kept the pace at around 7:15 min/km I could&amp;rsquo;ve run the whole 5k still struggling, but without slowing down or have my breathing go out of control.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Friday was an easy recovery run.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But that&amp;rsquo;s also when I started feeling a pain in my ribs. I had a slightly annoying feeling in my ribs since monday morning, when stretching after waking up. Which i thought was just me having slept in a weird position or something similar and I only felt it when I fully extended my arms which put a lot of pressure in my ribcage.&lt;br>
At the end of the friday run, I had pain on the right side my ribcage while taking deep breaths which later throughout the day also happened on any major movement like sitting down/getting up or lifting something heavy enough for the muscles near the area to engange. After a visit to my GP, I ended up with the diagnosis of it being an inflammation, possibly from some viral infection and a prescription for some pain killers.&lt;br>
Which led to me finding out that ibuprofen doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to do a good job for me on this, because as someone who usually falls asleep while lying on my side, that was impossible. I missed a lot of sleep the last 2 days and I have been in pain. No running at the moment. I hope that this will be gone in a few days.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But this is my 5k training plan done and now I have little bit of time to look for what to do next. I mentioned it in a previous post already, I am looking for a longer distance training plan, especially for a half marathon, which seems to be still managable timewise. I have looked at a few, nothing set in stone yet, might continue with the Nike HM plan, or maybe I might give the Garmin Coach Half Marathon feature which you have access to if you have a garmin watch a try, at least for a week or two to see what it will look like, since it seems to adapt itself to your performance. But I am meanwhile also looking at other plans, tons of them out there on the net.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s it for this week, thanks for reading. Hope to see you again!.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5k Plan: Week 7</title><link>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week7/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 20:18:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week7/</guid><description>&lt;p>Weekly Update #3&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another week gone by. Some unexpected things came up and I only got to do 3 runs:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://LiminalRunner.com/img/weekly/garmin2020-w26.jpg" alt="weekly_stats_2020_week26">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Monday was a hill interval workout at different speeds, a first for me. I was on a road that according to google maps should have around 6-7% inclination through a vineyard. I didn&amp;rsquo;t mind going uphill at all, but the fact that I had to go back down just to get up again between every interval was slightly annoying. I don&amp;rsquo;t like walking or running downhill in general.&lt;br>
Wednesday were flat intervals. I am learning that I really do enjoy intervals.&lt;br>
Friday was long run day with a 5k. Had the same problem as last week, that the first 1 or 2 km it just felt sluggish and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get into a comfortable pace. Don&amp;rsquo;t know what the problem is there, they were both run at an easy pace but it just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel good at the start. Maybe I need to do some warmup or something.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Coming week is the last of this 5k training plan and I am thinking about what to do after I am done with this plan. I know that I am not fast at all, but haven&amp;rsquo;t run 5k at an not easy pace, so I don&amp;rsquo;t really know what my time could be. So going for a faster 5k time could be something to work on. But I feel more drawn to increasing the distance. The 5k training plan I am using now is from Nike and offers Audio Guided Runs for every run, which I liked a lot. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen that they also offer this kind of plan for 10k, half marathon and marathon. I am thinking about aiming for that half marathon distance. Going from 5k to 21.1k is a lot not just the distance but also the time commitment. Long run days will take hours of my time, which is something I&amp;rsquo;ll have to consider. I&amp;rsquo;ll also have to think about hydration and/or nutrition. I never carried anything with me so far, because I knew I would be back home within an hour at the longest. I&amp;rsquo;ll also look into half marathon training plans that are available on the internet to see how they differ from the Nike one.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That is all, till next week.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5k Plan: Week 6</title><link>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week6/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 00:12:18 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week6/</guid><description>&lt;p>Weekly Update #2&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This was week 25 of 2020 and week 6 of the 5k Training Plan I am following.&lt;br>
Here are the stats from my watch, since it already flipped over to monday, the 7 day overview left out last monday, the 15th:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://LiminalRunner.com/img/weekly/garmin2020-w25.jpg" alt="weekly_stats_2020_week25">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Only had time to do 4 runs this week.&lt;br>
The missing Monday was an interval workout, Wednesday was a tempo run and the long run, which I did on Friday this week was for 6.5km / 4 Miles ( which ended up being 6.95km). Since these long runs are supposed to be run at an easy pace, the length itself wasn&amp;rsquo;t a problem at all. But the first 1-2km I had real problems finding that easy pace, but at around 2k I settled into a comfortable pace which i held (with small variations) to the end without much of a problem. Pretty happe with this weeks progress.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next weeks workouts include an interval run on a hill. The hills here go all over the place with inclination, so I am just going pick one and will keep going up that one. That workout will probably be hard on me, since the runs I always do are pretty much flat with only a small net elevation change.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>See you next post.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5k Plan: Week 5</title><link>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week5/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 23:50:55 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://LiminalRunner.com/posts/5k-week5/</guid><description>&lt;p>Weekly Update #1&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is week 24 of 2020 and today I finished week 5 of the Nike 5k Training Plan I am following.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are the stats from my Garmin watch:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://LiminalRunner.com/img/weekly/garmin2020-w24.jpg" alt="weekly_stats_2020_week24">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As you can see I managed to go on 5 runs, as per the training plan those were 2 tempo/interval runs, 2 recovery runs and 1 long run. The interval run on Tuesday was slightly longer than the actual long run, but thats to be expected on these &amp;ldquo;short&amp;rdquo; distances I guess.&lt;br>
I am pretty happy with how this week went down, weather was around 15-22°C for most of the week, just about right for me, but windy and rainy on 2 of the days. The only thing that felt off was the pacing, I went all over the place. Not sure if I somehow get influenced by the music I am listening to while the Audio Guides are silent or if I just suck at sticking to a pace in general, but that&amp;rsquo;s definitely something to work on, other than me being slow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next week the planend long run is for 6.5km or 4 Miles which is around the distance I ran before I stopped running over a year ago.&lt;br>
The tempo/interval runs in this training plan all have a 5 min warmup followed by optional stretching before the speed part which I&amp;rsquo;ve used to do some quick stretches which I remember from soccer practice almost 2 decades ago. I should look into what things to do for warmup, including for long and recovery runs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is all so far. Thank for reading this post. See you next Sunday (or maybe earlier).&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>